A Guide to the Papers of Thomas A. Mason
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Thomas A. Mason
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
14859
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are restrictions.
Acquisitions Information
These papers were given to Special Collections by Thomas A. Mason, Indianapolis, Indiana, on October 9, 2009.
Biographical/Historical Information
Thomas A. Mason was a Michigan native, who received his bachelor's degree in history from Kenyon College and his master's degree and doctorate from the University of Virginia. Formerly acting director and associate editor of The Papers of James Madison at the University of Virginia, he also was an assistant professor of history at Pembroke State University. He is currently project director of The Papers of Lew and Susan Wallace and an adjunct faculty member at Indiana University.
Scope and Content
This collection chiefly consists of the correspondence files of Thomas A. Mason, formerly one of the editors of The Papers of James Madison at the University of Virginia, 1958-2009, ca. 1,952 items (4 Hollinger boxes; 1.5 linear feet). Sometimes the correspondence files also contain additional materials about the correspondent, such as magazine and news clippings, obituaries, newsletters, and brochures.
Arrangement
The original alphabetical order by name of correspondent of the collection has been maintained.
Contents List
- 1979-2009 Correspondence-Ab-Ad, including: William Wright Abbot, University of Virginia History Professor; Henry Abraham, University of Virginia Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs; and Winthrop Lindsay Adams, University of Utah History Professor. (Box-folder 1:1)
- 1976-2005 Correspondence-Al-As, including: C. Knight Aldrich, University of Virginia professor of Medicine; Michael Van Cleave Alexander, Virginia Tech History Professor; Harry Lee Arnest III, graduate of the University of Virginia Architecture School and Graduate School of Arts and Sciences; and Robert Ashton, University of East Anglia School of English and American Studies Professor. (Box-folder 1:2)
- 1977-2006 Correspondence-Ba, including: Lance G. Banning, University of Kentucky History Professor; Madeleine Barry, English medical editor; Juxon Barton, English historian and correspondent; and Joan Baxter, former Secretary of University of Virginia Architecture School. (Box-folder 1:3)
- 1971-2003 Correspondence-Be, including: Sarah Beth Bearss, Editor at the Virginia Historical Society and Library of Virginia in Richmond; Francis Lewis Berkeley, Jr., Professor Emeritus at University of Virginia and University Archivist; Ronald Stanley Berman, Professor of English at Kenyon College and Chairman of the National Endowment for the Humanities; and Mary Hall Betts, Hostess of the Rotunda at University of Virginia. (Box-folder 1:4)
- 1976-1998 Correspondence-Bl-Bu, including: Mary Scott Parker Blake, Director of the Martha Jefferson House in Charlottesville; Joseph Norwood Bosserman, Dean of the School of Architecture at University of Virginia; Robin Bredin, teacher at Woodberry Forest School; Hugh J. Brent, 1974 University of Virginia Alumnus; Mildred Conrey Brown, Resident of Scottsville; and Frank Gerard Burke, Acting Archivist of the United States. (Box-folder 1:5)
- 1979-1999 Correspondence-(Dominic) Nghiep Cong Bui, Pembroke State University Assistant Librarian. (Box-folder 1:6)
- 1976-2006 Correspondence-C, including: Adelaine Callery, Michigan correspondent; John Canaday, University of Virginia Assistant Professor of Art and art critic for the New York Times; Charles Carlton, North Carolina State University History Professor; Robert Girard Carroon, Historiographer for Episcopal Diocese of Connecticut; Philander D. Chase, Editor of the University of Virginia Papers of George Washington; Douglas E. Clanin, Editor for the Indiana Historical Society; Sandra Sangeser Clark, Director of the Michigan Historical Center; Charles Frederick Williams Coker, Head of Reference and Reader Service Section in the Manuscripts Division at the Library of Congress; John Crisp Coleman, Assistant Professor of English at University of Virginia; Elizabeth Collier, English correspondent; Dennis M. Conrad, Editor of the Papers of Nathanael Greene and Editor at the Naval Historical Center; Lawrence D. Cress, associate Dean of Arts and Sciences at Willamette University; and Robert Dougherty Cross, University of Virginia Dean of the Faculty of Arts and Sciences. (Box-folder 1:7)
- 1979-2008 Correspondence-D, including: Cullom Davis, Editor of the Legal Papers of Abraham Lincoln; Edgar Glenn Davis, Vice President of Eli Lilly and Company in Indianapolis; Harry James Dell, History Professor at University of Virginia; Mary Sudman Donovan, Adjunct Professor of History at Hunter College; Ruth E. Dorrel, Editor for the Indiana Historical Society; Lindsay Gordon Dorrier, Commonwealth's Attorney; William S. Dudley, Editor at the Naval Historical Center and James Raynor Dunton, Washington Publisher. (Box-folder 1:8)
- 1980-2008 Correspondence-E-F, including: David K. Eliades, History professor at the University of North Carolina at Pembroke; John Leslie Finucane, Employee at the Naval Air Warfare Center; Florence Fleischman, Staff Liaison for Congressmen J. Kenneth Robinson and D. French Slaughter; Gerald P. Fogarty, Professor of the History of Christianity at University of Virginia; Emmett Brown Ford, Employee at the Office of Sponsored Programs at University of Virginia; and Anne Freudenberg, Curator of the Barrett Collection. (Box-folder 1:9)
- 1978-1988 Correspondence and Papers Related to-John Francis Flynn, Artist and Professor at Pembroke State University. (Box-folder 1:10)
- 1979-2004 Correspondence and Papers Related to-Peter M. Foley, Lawyer. (Box-folder 2:1)
- 1977-1995 Friday Club, Student Dining Club at University of Virginia. (Box-folder 2:2)
- 1977-2008 Correspondence-G, including: Muriel Kemp Ganser, Librarian at Lehigh University, Iowa State University, Bennington College, and more; James Gilreath, American History Specialist at the Library of Congress; Renée Gonse, English correspondent; and John Henry Greller, Vice President for Development at Northwestern College. (Box-folder 2:3)
- 1977-1999 Correspondence-Ha, including: Hattie P. Hall, correspondent; Charles Louis Hamilton, Assistant Professor of History at Kenyon College and Administrator at Simon Fraser University; William Henry Harbaugh, Professor of American History at University of Virginia; Charles Montreville Harris, Professor at Duquesne University and Editor of the Papers of William Thornton; and John Hattendorf, Kenyon College graduate and American Naval Historian. (Box-folder 2:4)
- 1972-1995 Correspondence-Martin Joseph Havran, Professor of History at University of Virginia. (Box-folder 2:5)
- 1996-2002 Correspondence-Martin Joseph Havran, Professor of History at University of Virginia. (Box-folder 2:6)
- 1977-2001 Correspondence-Ho, including: Eugene Pendleton Hogan, Author of fiction and nonfiction and resident of Charlottesville; David Holmes, Professor of Religious Studies and the College of William and Mary; Davyd Foard Hood, University of Virginia Architecture graduate; Alan Hornstein, Proffesseur at the Ecole Nationale Supérieure des Télécommunications in Paris, France; and Hampton P. Howell, Jr, stockbroker and resident of Charlottesville. (Box-folder 2:7)
- 1974-2005 Correspondence-I-Ll, including: Alfonso Lynn Ivey III, Richmond correspondent,; David Jackson, Delta airlines employee and resident of Isle of Palms, South Carolina; Bernice Jones, Bermuda correspondent; Mary Veronica Kuebel, PhD History; Charles Latham, teacher at the Episcopal Academy in Philadelphia; Emma Lents, Employee at Indiana Historical Society; Alexander Lind, Banker and Historian; Janet Linde, Archivist at University of Virginia and in New York; Samuel Thames Lloyd III, clergyman and Dean of Washington National Cathedral; and Marguerite Lloyd, University of Virginia graduate. (Box-folder 2:8)
- 1972-2003 Correspondence-Lo-Lu, including: Roger W. Lockyer, English Historian; Sir Gilbert Longden, English Member of Parliament; and Sister Julien Hill Lucy, French nun. (Box-folder 3:1)
- 1980-2002 Correspondence-Ma, including: Dumas Malone, American author of biography on Thomas Jefferson; Sally D. Mason, Editor of the Omohundro Institute of Early American History and Culture; Eleanor G. May, Professor of Business Administration at University of Virginia; and Margaret McClure MacLeod Mayo, Professor of History at University of Virginia and a resident of Charlottesville. (Box-folder 3:2)
- 1980-2002 Madison, Papers of James - History of the Project (Box-folder 3:3)
- 1986The Madisons of Montpelier- Manuscript Exhibition, Captions and keepsake (Box-folder 3:4)
- 1981-1987 Madison, James-Dictionary of American Biography article (Box-folder 3:5)
- 1962-2005 Correspondence-Mc-Me, including: J. Borden McCloskey, Proprietor of the Alcoholic Beverage Commission in Red Springs, north Carolina; Shirley Ann Snyder McCord, Editor at the Indiana Historical Society; Frances McCoughtry, Resident of Attica, Indiana and Ypsilanti, Michigan; James Sears McGee, Professor of the University of California, Santa Barbara; Judith Quintas McMullen, Editor at the Indiana Historical Society; John M. McNeary, Proprietor of a tree service company in Charlotte, North Carolina; Ernest C. Mead, Professor of Music at University of Virginia; Kenneth Meisel-Weisskopf, Swiss correspondent; and Arthur Mejia, San Francisco correspondent. (Box-folder 3:6)
- 1973- 1997 Correspondence-Mi- No, including: Joseph C. T. Miller, Professor of History at University of Virginia; William Lee Miller, Scholar in Ethics and Institutions at the Miller Center of Public Affairs at University of Virginia; Samuel Holt Monk, Professor of English at the University of Minnesota; Walter Bedford Moore, Assistant Professor of Humanities at University of Virginia; Peter Myles, English clergyman and correspondent; Louis John Nigro, U.S. Ambassador to Chad; and Elizabeth Copeland Norfleet, Author. (Box-folder 3:7)
- 1970- 2002 Correspondence-O-P, including: David Olyphant, Executive Director of the English-Speaking Union in New York; Olof Palme, Prime Minister of Sweden; William Brown Patterson, Professor of History at the University of the South; Elizabeth Pigg, Federal computer expert; James Playfair, English physician; and Patricia Power, Australian teacher. (Box-folder 3:8)
- 1975-1998 Correspondence-R-Ro, including: Michael Ramos, Lawyer; W. Ramsey Richardson, Clergyman; Andrew Richmond, Editor of Papers of Philander Chase; Jefferson D. Robinson III, Alumni Director at Kenyon College; Marie-Louise Roget, visiting Professor of French at University of Virginia; and Henry G. Roseveare, Professor of History at King's College in London. (Box-folder 3:9)
- 1996-2002 Correspondence-Robert Allen Rutland, Editor of Papers of James Madison at University of Virginia. (Box-folder 4:1)
- 1983-1995 Correspondence-Robert Allen Rutland, Editor of Papers of James Madison at University of Virginia. (Box-folder 4:2)
- 1984-2009 Correspondence-S-Sc, including: Thomas R. Sant, Lawyer and Kenyon College graduate; Hans Schmitt, Professor of History at University of Virginia; and William Remsen Schultz. (Box-folder 4:3)
- 1974-2003 Correspondence-Se-Sha, including: Edward Carl Wolfram von Selzam, German Diplomat; David A. Shannon, Provost at University of Virginia; and Ronald Sharp, Professor of English at Kenyon College. (Box-folder 4:4)
- 1983-2008 Correspondence-She-So, including: Chester Price Shelly, Michigan Accountant and godfather of Thomas Mason; Charlotte J. Shelton, Charlottesville stockbroker; Joan Shivel, Williamsburg, Virginia correspondent; Edward F. Shotter, English clergyman and correspondent; Richard Stuart Simons, Indiana Historian; Jerry N. Showalter, bookseller; Susan Slade, Indianapolis architectural historian; Lewis M. Slater, Lawyer in Detroit; and Earl Phillip Sourwine, Indianapolis banker. (Box-folder 4:5)
- 1975-2004 Correspondence-St-Ti, including: Victor Andrew Stock, English clergyman and correspondent; Anton J. Streiff, Administrator at Carnegie Mellon University; Peter Taylor, J. Garland Teasley, Clergyman and correspondent; Edward Riggs Telling III, Lawyer in Rockford, Illinois; Alexander C. von Thelen, Harriet Gayle Thornbrough, Executive Secretary of the Indiana Historical Society; and Marie Leslie Shackelford Tise, librarian in Delaware. (Box-folder 4:6)
- 1982-2005 Correspondence-Tu-V, including: Eve Turnball, Hostess of the Rotunda at University of Virginia; Dory Twitchell (see also Montpelier), Administer at Montpelier; Nicholas Tyacke, Professor of History at the University College, London; Irene Ashworth Valentine, Charlottesville resident and correspondent; and John Stanley Vishneski, Chicago Lawyer. (Box-folder 4:7)
- 1958, 1972-2003 Correspondence-W, including: Joseph Addison Warren; Michigan Lawyer; James B. Watson, London small-press printer; William Stone Weedon, Chairman of the Philosophy Department at University of Virginia; Minor Tompkins Weisiger, librarian at the Library of Virginia; Herman B. Wells, Chancellor at Indiana University; Michael L. Westfall, Hospital Administrator and Board member of Historical Organizations in Indiana; Sir. John Wheeler-Bennett, Historical Adviser for the Royal Archives; and Michael Cunningham Williams, Washington Lawyer. (Box-folder 4:8)